<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="people.xsl" ?>
<data>
<persons>
<person>
<title>Angelos Barmpoutis</title>
<description><![CDATA[Angelos Barmpoutis is currently a Professor and coordinator of research and technology in the Digital Worlds Institute at the University of Florida. He is also an affiliate faculty of the Computer and Information Science and Engineering Department and the Biomedical Engineering Department, University of Florida. His current research projects focus on automated analysis of human motion, 3D reconstruction and dissemination of digital cultural heritage, applications of virtual and augmented reality, and medical image analysis. For his contribution to the aforementioned areas, he received in 2014 the Merit Award from the IEEE International Conference on Connected Vehicles, in 2016 he was finalist for the Rome Prize for Historic Preservation and Conservation, and was named UF Research Foundation Professor for 2020-2023. Dr. Barmpoutis has coauthored numerous highly cited publications in the aforementioned topics, and his work has led to patented and copyrighted inventions registered in the US, and been funded by several awards and grants from various funding agencies including the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, the National Endowment for the Humanities, the National Institutes of Health, and the US Department of Transportation. In the international community he is also known for the Digital Epigraphy and Archaeology project that he is directing since 2011 and the highly cited Java-For-Kinect open-source library, which has been continuously used since 2013 in more than 50 countries around the world.]]></description>
<MicrosoftAcademic>https://academic.microsoft.com/profile/72776397-00h0-48h9-e90h-j8i3h11i29e7/AngelosBarmpoutis/</MicrosoftAcademic>
<GoogleScholar>https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=XHdA6fIAAAAJ</GoogleScholar>
<Scopus><![CDATA[http://www.scopus.com/authid/detail.url?origin=AuthorProfile&authorId=15520955600]]></Scopus>
<ORCID>https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3271-7965</ORCID>
<ACMProfile>https://dl.acm.org/profile/81317490738</ACMProfile>
<IEEEProfile>https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/author/37294293100</IEEEProfile>
<URL>https://research.dwi.ufl.edu/people/angelos</URL>
</person>

<person>
<title>Marko  Suvajdzic</title>
<description><![CDATA[A diverse thinker with 19+ years of achievement in academia and the creative digital research and production space. Marko’s experience includes a range of digital startups and educational projects from artificial Intelligence-intensive video game titles for major corporate clients to co-founding  5 of his own startups.
\n
\nMarko was the founder of the Computer Arts Department at the Academy of Art in Serbia, and serves as the CEO of the multi-national game studio O2D, Inc. He has lectured internationally at schools and conferences in the U.S.A., U.K., India, Serbia, China, and Norway.
\n<h4>a. Professional Preparation</h4>
\nUniversity of Arts in Belgrade, Serbia            Theory of Arts and Media                    Ph.D.   (2016)
\nAcademy of Art University, USA                     Photography                                        M.F.A. (2000)
\nUniversity of North Florida, USA                    Computer Information Systems          B.S.     (1996)
\n<h4>b. Appointments</h4>
\n2023-present  Professor, Digital Arts and Sciences, University of Florida
\n2014-2023   Associate Professor, Digital Arts and Sciences, University of Florida
\n2014-present   Associate Director, Innovation and Entrepreneurship, Digital Worlds Institute, University of Florida
\n2005-present   Co-Founder/CEO, O2D Interactive Studio, San Francisco/Belgrade
\n2013-2014       Visiting Assistant Professor, Digital Arts and Sciences, University of Florida
\n2003-2012       Department Chair, Computer Arts and Design, Academy of Art, Belgrade Serbia
\n2008-2012       Associate Professor, Advertising and Design, Academy of Art, Belgrade Serbia
\n2003-2008       Assistant Professor, Computer Arts and Design, Academy of Art, Belgrade Serbia
\n2000-2001       VP of Production, Bigprizes.com, San Francisco
\n1999-2000       Creative Director, Audiocafe.com, San Francisco]]></description>
</person>

<person>
<title>James Oliverio</title>
<description><![CDATA[James Oliverio is internationally known as a creative artist, researcher, educator, and producer, and is a frequent keynote speaker and consultant to digital media industry and education programs. He has served as Executive Director of the Digital Worlds Institute at the University of Florida since January 2001, with full professorships in Digital Arts &amp; Sciences and in Music. He holds five Emmy Awards from the Atlanta chapter of the National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences. His work has been funded by agencies including the National Endowment for the Arts, the National Science Foundation, and the Reader’s Digest Foundation. His work in internationally-distributed performing and digital arts has been featured on CNN International and the BBC.
\n
\nOliverio’s orchestral scores have been commissioned and premiered by ensembles including the Cleveland Orchestra and the symphonies of Atlanta, Columbus, and Pittsburgh, in addition to performances at Carnegie Hall and the Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts in Washington, DC. Oliverio has produced for and collaborated with Jazz @ Lincoln Center, the New York Philharmonic, the New York City Ballet and the Film Society of Lincoln Center, and served as Artistic Consultant on a number of projects with jazz legend Wynton Marsalis. Prior to becoming the Founding Director of the Digital Worlds Institute, Oliverio served as the Artist in Residence at the Georgia Institute of Technology, and also as Founding Director of AudioLab in the Graphics, Visualization and Usability Center in the Georgia Tech College of Computing.]]></description>
</person>

<person>
<title>Hyo jeong Kang</title>
<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
</person>

<person>
<title>Markus Santoso</title>
<description><![CDATA[Markus Santoso holds a Ph.D. degree from Dongseo University, South Korea. His main research interests are Augmented and Virtual Reality, Wearable Technologies, NUI, UX/UI, and Serious-game Development. He graduated in 2013 and went to Erfurt, Germany to continue his research as a Postdoctoral Fellow at the Fraunhofer IDMT under a funding scheme from the European Research Consortium for Informatics and Mathematics (ERCIM). To enter this fellowship program, Markus needed to compete with more than 300 PhDs worldwide; only 24 applications were approved. As an ERCIM fellow, Markus had the opportunity to visit other well-known European research institutes as research intern such as INRIA MimeTIC at Rennes-France with a focus on VR and at VTT in Espoo-Finland doing research in AR. After that, Markus conducted his 2nd postdoctoral with the LINDSAY Virtual Human Lab at the University of Calgary, Canada. He received an Eyes-high Postdoctoral fellowship and worked on the implementation of AR/MR for human anatomy illustration, medical education, and computational physiology. Markus also had several industrial experiences with AR/VR-related startup companies in various capacities such as Hololens Developer at Wellness Computation in Calgary, Canada and Head of Department of Licensing and Gamification Department at Octagon Studio. Starting from July 2018 Markus starts his tenure-track position at University of Florida.]]></description>
</person>

<person>
<title>Amelia Winger-Bearskin</title>
<description><![CDATA[Amelia Winger-Bearskin is an artist who innovates with artificial intelligence in ways that make a positive impact on our community and the environment. She is a<a href=https://news.ufl.edu/archive/2014/02/banks-family-commits-5-million-to-support-university-of-floridas-preeminence-i.html> Banks Family Preeminence Chair</a> and Associate Professor of <a href=https://news.ufl.edu/2020/07/nvidia-partnership/>Artificial Intelligence and the Arts</a>, at the <a href=https://digitalworlds.ufl.edu/>Digital Worlds Institute</a> at the University of Florida. She is the inventor of Honor Native Sky, a project for the U.S. Department of Arts and Culture: <a href=https://usdac.us/nativeland>Honor Native Land Initiative.</a> She founded Wampum.Codes which is both an award-winning <a href=http://wampum.codes/>podcast</a> and an <a href=https://foundation.mozilla.org/en/blog/indigenous-wisdom-model-software-design-and-development/>ethical framework for software development </a>based on indigenous values of co-creation. Wampum.codes was awarded a Mozilla Fellowship embedded at the MIT Co-Creation Studio from 2019-2020 and was featured at the 2021 <a href=https://imaginenative.org/>imagineNative </a>festival. She continued her research in 2021 at Stanford University as their artist and technologist in residence made possible by the Stanford Visiting Artist Fund in Honor of Roberta Bowman Denning (VAF) .
\n
\nIn 2019 she was an invited presenter to His Holiness, The 14th Dalai Lama, at his World Headquarters in Dharamsala for the Summit on Fostering Universal Ethics and Compassion. In 2018 she was awarded a MacArthur/Sundance Institute fellowship for her 360 video immersive installation in collaboration with the artist Wendy Red Star (supported by the Google JUMP Creator program). The non-profit she founded IDEA New Rochelle, in partnership with the New Rochelle Mayor’s Office, won the 2018 $1 Million Dollar Bloomberg Mayor’s Challenge for their VR/AR Citizen toolkit to help the community co-design their city.  In 2018 she was awarded the 100k Alternative Realities Prize for her Virtual Reality Project from Engadget and Verizon Media. Amelia is the founder of the <a href=http://www.stupidhackathon.com/>stupidhackathon.com</a>.
\n
\nAmelia is Indigenous:  Seneca-Cayuga Nation of Oklahoma, Deer Clan, Haudenosaunee (Iroquois).]]></description>
<Linkedin>https://linkedin.com/in/ameliawb</Linkedin>
<Medium>https://studioamelia.medium.com/</Medium>
<MozillaPulse>https://www.mozillapulse.org/profile/3119/about</MozillaPulse>
<MITFellow>http://opendoclab.mit.edu/presents/amelia-winger-bearskin-fellow/</MITFellow>
<URL>http://studioamelia.com</URL>
</person>

<person>
<title>Wenbin Guo</title>
<description><![CDATA[<span style=font-weight: 400;>Wenbin Guo is a Postdoc Associate at UF Digital Worlds Institute. He collaborates with an interdisciplinary team from Digital Worlds Institute, the Center of Arts in Medicine, and the Center for the Arts, Migration, and Entrepreneurship to automate analysis and annotation of human motion using artificial intelligence. He builds and runs deep learning algorithms on existing human datasets of video and skeletal sequences. He received his Ph.D. in Industrial Engineering along with a Master of Computer Science at the University of Missouri. As an independent researcher, much of his focus has been on AR/VR, human-computer interaction, healthcare, and machine learning. He developed an advanced location-based augmented reality learning environment. He was motivated to improve personnel performance in the healthcare system. He also developed a serverless conversational survey platform AI chatbot helping non-technical persons to build and deploy customized surveys using conversations.</span>]]></description>
</person>

</persons>

</data>